[Music]
hi
this is eric with a few thoughts for
this week's housekeeping what i want to
bring up this week is how to think about
the portal podcast
and in particular i want to give a few
thoughts on how we should measure the
scale of a critique
or the power of an idea and how these
two different concepts might interrelate
many years ago i used to live in
cambridge massachusetts and we had our
own very peculiar notion of celebrities
back then i mean tracy chapman literally
used to bust on the street for money
and npr's car talk guys lived locally it
was within that milieu that i would go
to talks for entertainment
as a broke graduate student lecturers
were a godsend as they were free and
plentiful
i would attend them the way other people
would go to movies or concerts and from
time to time that would include noam
chomsky's lectures on political theory
as he worked at mit
i was always impressed by his sincerity
and sometimes i would stay after and
talk with him
on one such occasion i told him that i
had had a conversation with a contacted
npr
and that that person might be interested
in getting him a regular slot
of perhaps five minutes or more i was
naturally very excited to make something
like this happen if it were in fact
possible
gnome's response was surprising to me at
the time he was absolutely emphatic that
he was not interested
somewhat stung i asked him why he was so
definite
he replied in such a small slot against
a backdrop of npr-filtered news he would
appear to the audience to be a
stark-raving madman
and that there was no way of presenting
a deep critique so as to overcome the
relentless framing of the news into
narratives in which
npr was engaging i have thought about
that interchange many times since then
as i have been haunted by its
implications
what good after all is a chomsky level
analysis if it is barred from having any
impact when done at scale
when we have a critique of a well-known
narrative or worldview it usually can be
sorted into a taxonomy according to
whether it accepts
bends or is forced to break the frame of
the storyline with which it contends
as an example imagine we were back in
2016 and i were to critique the coverage
of the u.s presidential election for
failing to contend with the ideas of
donald trump
saying that i feel that we aren't
covering trump sufficiently because we
all know that hillary is going to win
would constitute a critique but one that
accepts the narrative without challenge
saying instead hillary is going to beat
donald trump by much less than she
imagines and will have to build her
mandate after the inauguration if she is
to be effective
would bend the hillary's inevitable
media narrative
but saying instead i think all the
pundits and polls are wrong and that
donald trump should be expected to win
would break the narrative entirely this
breaking of the frame is usually cause
for derision
and is of course exactly what got ann
coulter
ridiculed on bill maher's program when
she made just that prediction
to return to our story in massachusetts
almost all of chomsky's points were in
fact narrative breakers in this third
category
he would have stories we'd never heard
from east timor detailed history on
iranian self-determination and oil
reserves data on chilean atrocities
to accept chomsky was to accept a world
of different stories that
oddly enough could usually be
authenticated but which were frequently
not referenced
outside far left circles thus chomsky
could not play inside the game of npr
which was often bending and sometimes
challenging official narratives
but seldom ever breaking the dominant
frames within which the storylines
developed
in short planet chomsky was an
alternative universe in which a howard
zinn might be found
but where you would never find samuel
huntington or henry kissinger
i mean they might have taught down the
street at harvard in the adjacent zip
code one digit off but it was another
incompatible universe entirely so what
can one say about the style of deep
critique which must break the frame of
its target without knowing any further
information
well in the first place no one can
really argue that all frame breaking is
unwarranted
i mean clearly the u.s view of north
korea is such a critique for example
as is the mainstream baptist critique of
an offshoot cult
like the hate-fueled westboro baptist
church and yet
when the narrative under scrutiny is our
own narrative the very one upon which we
depend
to give direction meaning and security
in our daily lives
we can be relied upon to fight
everything that breaks our frame
irrespective of its validity so with
this in mind in the covid pandemic
response as our backdrop
who are today's deep critics and should
we be listening to them or ignoring them
as is our reflex
well i'm glad to say that noam chomsky
is still going strong and i dare to
think that upon his eventual exit from
this world
he may well be remembered as america's
leading public intellectual
even by many of the respectable people
who paid him absolutely no mind while he
was still a living threat to our system
nasim tuleb of course is another
candidate now televised idiosyncrasy is
notwithstanding
it is particularly difficult to contend
with the substance of teleps critique
because it is so vast
where other people trade accusations
about the misuse of statistics
telev verges on saying that the field of
statistics is itself the problem
while some might argue about the fallacy
of appeal to authority in a particular
case
taleb instead goes after many of the
expert class by name endearing himself
to his targets by calling them
i y i for intellectual yet idiot
he does this i believe because he wants
to signal that all frames coming from
the mainstream
should be considered dead on arrival
with him unless verified from first
principles
a third case might have been my old
friend and colleague serge lang
at yale who i may discuss another time
as he is no longer with us
and i will leave scott alexander
venkatesh rao peter thiel
nick bostrom and others for another time
my aim in bringing up these various and
varied critics
is to bring to consciousness that there
is actually almost no real information
content in pointing out that we disagree
with
nearly any deep frame breaking critique
if it's targeted upon our own narratives
this must be the baseline expectation if
we wish to see ourselves as self-aware
and metacognitive
we oppose most all such critics
reflexively and completely independent
of the merit of their arguments for
reasons of self-preservation
and yet and yet even knowing this my
goal at the portal is at least in part
to provide you the listener with just
such a deep critique
the problem here is that the critique as
it stands is simply so vast that it is
difficult to consider
independent of whether or not it makes
sense or is true
think for example about the past
episodes we've been through
we've asked you to rethink science and
its culture from the bottom up
the portal in fact began with an
interview about stagnation during a
period where most everyone else was
talking about some dizzying pace of
technological change
we've explored the idea of universal
societal lies and preference
falsification and the idea that judaism
might not even be a religion
and most insanely the need to stave off
an apocalypse
potentially through planetary escape
well before we were all told to stay
indoors as a planet to avoid a killer
virus i mean
if there is a silver lining to this
pandemic here at the portal it is surely
that our talk about the twin nuclei
problem on the joe rogan program and
worldwide apocalypse seems a lot less
far-fetched
after transitioning suddenly from
business as usual to worldwide lockdown
so how can this be done at scale without
paying the same exact reflexive penalty
of cognitive dissonance as all the other
deep critics seem to have suffered
if there is an answer here it is to be
found in the concept of the portal
itself
my goal is not to tell you that where we
are is terrible and contains no
meaningful options
the highest ambition in fact of the
program is to show you how else you
might think about finding passages to
something real and more meaningful than
the place you were when we first met
after that if you want to remain in
place that would be a choice rather than
a sentence
so what i want to leave you with is a
notion which i believe goes back to
richard dawkins
at some point he opined that one could
measure the power of an idea as if it
were a fraction
to this way of thinking the power of an
idea is measured as
what the idea explains divided by what
the idea is forced to assume
for example dawkins might claim that the
theory of evolution is powerful
specifically because it explains the
origin of all known species and
adaptations
but only assumes the principles of
natural and sexual selection
maxwell's equations by contrast are
powerful because they explain light
x-rays radio waves magnetism electricity
photons all as an unpacking of a single
geometric concept
weber's theory by turns that all
government can oddly be unpacked from
the simple concept
of a monopoly on violence would be such
a theory in the social rather than the
natural sciences
as such it may be easier to accept
darwin's maxwell's and weber's critiques
of all that came before them
specifically because their criticism is
not scattered and flows simply from
unifying and underlying principles
in the case of the portal we have
endeavored to follow this example
quite simply and there's no getting
around this our critique of modern life
is
partially characterized by just how deep
it is yes we are really saying that we
have had a universally unworkable
leadership class in place
for nearly 50 years and that most of our
institutions are not functioning
ethically or honestly
in other words most of us adults grew up
in a bubble
of course that probably sounded a lot
crazier to many before most people saw
the worldwide clown show that was and is
the developed world's response to the
covid19 pandemic
but just imagine that almost every
critical area of civil society
leadership is
just as badly prepared as our public
health sector to react to immediate
changes in need and you will start to
watch your brain tune out
as it may well have during initial
discussion of the virus in january
after all what would one do to fix it i
mean i myself get innervated just like
you whenever i think about the most
straightforward implications
where would we even begin for god's
sakes yet this is why we have endeavored
to provide you with a very small
denominator to combat the sense of
hopelessness
i mean if there is more or less only one
root cause to the problems we are
picking out
then our idea will have power in the
sense of dawkins and we need not work
individually on thousands of
idiosyncratic downstream emergencies
clamoring for our attention in our
theory almost all of this novel level of
systemic failure and institutional
leadership
follows from a simple change in growth
regimes in the post-war regime from 1945
until the early 1970s
growth was so remarkable and constant
that we built our institutions around
expectations of economic expansion and
technological innovation
and then just like that most all of that
growth stopped around 1971 through 1973
maybe having to do with predictions of
derek desola price more than 10 years
earlier
which we can discuss another time like
weber's theory of a monopoly on violence
or darwin's explanation of selection
the validity of this simplification
rests on what can be unpacked from
relatively mild assumptions
through the theory of embedded growth
obligations because these institutions
are all facing the same system of
pressures there is a near universal need
for every titular head in this cohort of
leaders
to hide the fact that their institution
is predicated on high growth
expectations
and that they are all now failing and
that the expectations cannot be met
further if this is correct they are
failing in exactly the same ways with
the same class and type of leaders at
the helm
whose top skill must be this masking of
the inability of the leadership to meet
the growth obligation embedded within
the foundations of their institutions
simply to keep the game going this is
what must now come to an end
generations are in fact defined by their
cognitive development during whatever
environment was present during their
formative years
the important generational divide is
likely between the silent and baby boom
generations on one side who grew up as
children and young adults amidst real
growth
and who are thus attached to the
narratives of success under difficult
circumstances
with gen x and the millennials still
waiting their turn and largely alienated
from narratives which offer them very
little
other than debt and near permanent
holding patterns once the baby boomers
in silence exit the system we are likely
to see their successors start to
actually admit to the terrible state of
the institutions
so if you're interested in this theory
this is now your homework assignment
as you watch this cohort of leaders
wrestle with the covid pandemic
ask yourself what part of the bizarre
nature of this response can be deduced
from the theory of embedded growth
obligations we have now spent in the
united states the last
28 years under baby boomer
administrations so
how well did they do to prepare us for
this pandemic did they leave us
stockpiles of essential supplies
did they resign when they failed in
their duties are their instincts
compatible with the heavy burdens which
are now likely to cascade from here
and if pandemic leads to depression and
depression leads to war
would you wish to send yourself or a
child into battle under president
sanders president
trump or president biden as
commander-in-chief or would you look for
a portal instead to avoid this choice
this portal episode introduces you to
one of my favorite people and favorite
artists on earth
now let me say this if you were to ask
me which of my guests so far is most
often an open portal to the transcendent
this is the one
and i've seldom been as certain as i am
here it's hard to know what to say about
ilu aka eric lewis
two things however are clear he is a
straight-up genius and a force of nature
are we friends i definitely say yes but
it is a strange thing to be friends with
an avalanche or a tsunami
at a shabbat dinner table for example
he's one of our favorite guests but he
often speaks to me in riddles and
sometimes reminds me in speech of how
jimi hendrix used to struggle to talk to
mortals
and in many ways beyond that the
comparison seems a good one
if one looks at the musical notation
meant to say what hendrix was doing on
guitar
it is remarkable how little is captured
this is because hendrix expanded the
dimensionality of the guitar with
feedback micro embellishments and
electronic wizardry
so that the notes provided only the
barest substrate for the tapestry of
sound that was being woven
in many ways eric has done the same
thing for the piano
so just as les paul preceded hendricks
in using the studio as an instrument and
flamenco artists were tapping on
fretboards long before eddie van halen
changed the percussive guitar game
eric was not the first to play with the
internal organs of the piano to coax out
new sounds
but far beyond the prepared piano
experiments of art music composers
when eric ripped the cover off the piano
to play both the keys and the harp-like
strings behind
he brought so much dimensionality and
soul that he at last overcame the
critical limitation of the instrument
that had plagued it since his birth
the piano's mechanical action which is
one of the great triumphs of pure
mechanical engineering
ensured that there was regularity to
most every note
eric replaced that regularity and
created a higher dimensional instrument
if the piano was einstein to the
harpsichord's newton
in eric's hands the piano went
relativistic in quantum finally at the
same time
i should say that this is one of many
different innovations that eric has
brought
he has explored the fusion of baroque
counterpoint and jazz into a style that
he calls counter bop which quite frankly
stretches my mind farther than it can
often go
as well as innovating rock jazz to
replace the tin pan alley song book of
standards
additionally he has innovated in several
aspects of showmanship as well as djing
and screenwriting which
is hardly surprising as my entire body
can seemingly fit inside his brain case
as for this interview a word of warning
i should say that eric is being very
kind to me indeed by inviting me to at
least pretend to play along with him
either on the high registers of the
piano while he is playing
or using the clogged harmonica that i
happen to find in my pocket
the morning we recorded in la on a
famous yamaha that was apparently used
to record angie by the rolling stones
i would appreciate it if you didn't see
it as me getting in his way so much
as an act of supreme generosity from a
true innovator and friend to a humbled
curator
i hope you will look into eric's music
after you've had a chance to listen to
our uninterrupted conversation and
you'll sit back relax and meet the
portal that is my friend ilu
eric lewis
[Music]
hello you found the portal i'm here
today with one of my favorite people and
our guest eric lewis
alias ilu i don't exactly know how to
describe
what he is and what he does but we'll
start with pianist
and we'll go from there because he's
also a dj screenwriter
and a guy who uh one of well one of the
reasons he's on the show is that it
seems like everything he touches he has
to innovate so ilu welcome to the portal
hi thanks eric so one of the things i
just want to jump right into
is that i'm super frustrated with where
music has been recently
and i think it's really interesting that
you occur in our era from my perspective
a lot of our popular music has been
getting simpler as it was getting more
intricate and more dependent on
musicianship
back in the 70s and a lot of what we're
seeing is a
shift to the studio to simpler forms and
you come along and for my money you are
innovating
at the very highest levels of jazz
rock and pop all at the same time are
you seeing something like that
where you were somehow like a salmon
swimming counter to the stream or do you
think that you're just
a part of our age and in fact it's the
same as it ever was
thank you first of all
for saying that
i think of myself as just
an arch traditionalist in some sense
part of the tradition of jazz
with a nod of the hat
or an eye on miles davis
john coltrane arctatum
you know part of the tradition of jazz
is
to innovate and to
indeed individuate as carl young might
say perhaps
you know that is the focus
that i find myself orbiting
and that's my pursuit i've sort of
painted myself in a corner
in a lot of different ways and i use
that
sort of sense of being trapped or
forced to commit to this thing that i've
painted myself into a corner with
and i use that particular
situation that particular scenario to
drive out and bring
forth innovation as they say ingenuity
what is that necessity as the mother of
ingenuity or
mother of invention well that's just the
thing so if
for for people who don't know you and
they're going to not only know you
hopefully but we have a beautiful yamaha
piano behind us they're going to feel
you
uh shortly um let me just give you
sort of a non-musician's impression
of where i've seen you innovating okay
first of all you've taken what used to
be called prepared piano where people
would leave like bricks and paper clips
in the back of the piano
and you've stuck your hand in there to
coax all sorts of sounds out
that add a such a rich dimensionality to
your playing that
you have access to many more degrees of
freedom than a standard person
so you're playing in the back and in the
front of the piano
you've innovated this idea which you
called rock jazz which was a canonical
innovation in that originally when jazz
was coming up
people used the popular songs of the day
as the substrate on which to improvise
and you you pointed out that you know
autumn leaves is not a part of our
current canon
it's a part of our older canon so why
not use the rock songs that everyone
knows is the substrate to be
true not to the letter but to the spirit
of jazz which is to use that which
everyone knows and show them something
they don't
huge innovation um like all of the best
uh you know jerry lee lewis footage
where he kicks away the
the the bench and he's just playing
standing there you've got this
in insane powerful stance you use this
armor
to you know to convey the aggression
and i think you know i always talk about
the violence of creativity one of the
reasons we're afraid of creativity is
that we're afraid that it
created creativity is always a violent
act you came up with this thing called
counter bop where you're bringing sort
of bach-like
counterpoint into a into the jazz idiom
and achieving a level of independence uh
we say of your hands but of parts of
your mind that i've never
i don't think i've ever seen at the at
the keyboard
to say nothing of how you've innovated
uh i'm starting to hear that you're
djing from inside of the piano
it feels to me like everything you touch
is a response
to a constraint that you take on the
constraints of the traditional
and then you force yourself houdini-like
to break out of them
is that an accurate description of what
it is that's driving this sort of
explosion
i would say that most of it is accurate
some of it would be argued
from the perspective of branding and
that sort of kind of thing but isn't
that part of
the tradition right so so there's that
you know that's part of creativity too
and it's important as well so
i would definitely say that counter bop
of all of
the innovations is one that's
got the heaviest musical
academic durability
i would say that rock jazz was
innovative
however i'm not the first person to play
rock tunes or rock covers on a piano
i think i might be the first person to
sort of go at it with the ferocity
and the physical degree of power and
endurance
and sort of
fidelity to those pieces
so i think that i go about that
particular endeavor in an innovative way
branding it as rock jazz perhaps that's
innovative
and using that as a wedge
to create an extension of my career
so you know there's an innovative
quality there i would say counter bob
which is a more recent situation more
recent device
that i've come up with that's something
that i can definitely say is
innovative in the sense that
i really haven't heard anyone
mix bach counterpoint with bebop
there's a lot of people that have
brought
baroque counterpoint european
counterpoint
into jazz however
and this is for all of the people who
are going to
immediately pounce on this statement or
scream
wail that oh it has been done before
actually no
it hasn't it hasn't been done in a
swinging way
so the idea that jazz doesn't have to
swing
or that sort of kind of a thing right
that's going to be a thing and that
particular
wormhole right there can go very deep
but suffice to say
that no playing
bach counterpoint or that sort of kind
of a thing
inside of jazz is very different from
counter bop which is why i call it
counter bop right it's not counter point
it's counter bop so that you have
two bud powell or two charlie parker
like lines full of all of their internal
striations and internal
acrobatics shall we say harmonic melodic
acrobatics
working within the traditions of swing
and
the traditions of bebop at the same time
simultaneously
there are a couple of pianists that
do have some very highly developed left
hands
that are able to do it to a degree and
perhaps
a good degree but i haven't heard anyone
get it to like the highest levels
and i believe that i've found a way to
you know
i have to say this because i'm not a
jazz guy i don't have some of the
problems that you have
we just there's an elephant in the room
and i want to kill it at the beginning
which is
jazz is such an intellectual pursuit and
it's
so discriminating as to the fine points
of one's ability
that it really is a mount olympus and
it's left
most of the world behind and so you
always have this problem that when
you're talking the small number of jazz
cats who can really
track what you're saying and who know
the history like they're historians of
the subject
will always pounce any simple statement
is going to be wrong
you know and then they'll point you to
something that happened in you know with
django reinhardt
you know way back when and and you it's
incredibly intimidating to have to work
within this tradition
one of the things i've most appreciated
about you
is the way in which you're willing to
both take on the constraints
and totally uh overturn the apple cart
at the same time so that you're really
true to the spirit
and i think the people who will resist
you at first will thank you later
um if you think about you know ray
charles for example who wasn't
quite you know at this level of jazz
mastery but as an innovator
brought gospel into the popular idiom
boy did he catch hell for that
um or you know playing around with
country idioms you know the the black
guy taking on
supposedly white songs and showing what
can be done with them
i think that one has to to to break
sensibilities and norms and one of the
things i don't want to get caught up in
is have you self-censoring yourself so
i'm going to take full responsibility
for all the wrong things that we say
about jazz history on this
show not your problem my problem
what do you see uh for people
who don't understand the difference
between let's say
uh a miles davis and a kenny g
nothing against kenny g what what are
the top
people in this field uh do differently
how did america
end up with a classical music that was
this advanced this quickly and and who
are the
who are the really top priests at the
pinnacle of that summit
for you okay so that's a
solid and complex multi-faceted octopus
question
uh-oh which is fine it's understandable
okay i'm a big fan of science
and i try to exploit the scientific
method whenever possible
so from the perspective of the human
animal
you know every sort of
opinion about this or that as far as
sound goes or as far as
as far as certitude or validity
for instance if you put kenny g's name
next to miles davis name
i think that it's difficult to have a
truly acerbic scientific
conversation about that there's going to
be those that feel as though kenny g
is the greatest musician that's ever
lived
and there's going to be those that think
that miles davis
is the greatest musician that ever lived
and then
there will be those that think that the
idea of
calling someone the greatest musician
that ever lived israel
itself yeah this flawed i agree with
that and
has a bias inherent in it that
intrinsically undermines
the sort of conversation or the purity
the purity no no it's fine no no it's
fine i i
i feel as though it's important as far
as
in the process of me answering your
question and sure in the process of you
getting a sense of who i am and how
you know i feel about things or how i
you know classify things
so that answers the first aspect of
my approach to comparison got it
so existentially speaking
they're sort of the same depending upon
you know for instance
you could do a mind hack where you turn
on a television
and switch the channel to something that
just gives you white noise
right now you can do a mind hack where
you could hear jingle bells inside of
that white noise you can pretty much
hear whatever you're listening cage
certainly explored ideas like that
right you can hear whatever you're
listening for in something
and this goes to politics this goes to
this goes all the way out into all of
human thought and bias endeavors right
so i shot i'm a chess player so i shy
away from
that particular battle line i'm going to
shy away
from putting a qualitative or a sort of
a validate
valid validation oriented thing with
regards to
the kenny g versus the miles let me take
kenny g out of it
i think it's a no it's a perfect example
actually you're not going to let me out
of it okay
but it's perfect though all right it's
perfect riff with it yeah
yeah it's perfect the extremities
always allow us to get to clarity as far
as i'm concerned and that's a big aspect
of what i look at when i'm evaluating
things you know
the more extreme something is the more
pronounced it is the purer it is and the
easier
we can see how it functions
in reality our political climate is one
of extremes these days
so then it's very clear everyone's
agendas are very clear
and so we can see how those things
interact and where they agree where they
disagree and
you know the basis is upon the bases
the basis is base cc's or whatever that
word is the plural basis
the bases upon which each extreme side
proffers you know their position to be
concrete well anyway so when it comes to
the aspect of classifying levels of
greatness in musicians and stuff like
that
that becomes a difficult thing
to nail down because of
the movable objective criteria the
the attackability of the objective
criteria that we would try to put out
there
right but what we can talk about we can
talk about branding
we can say or we can talk about physical
difficulties we can talk about
things like that um i'm trying to
remember
you know all of the question but
i can say that as far as who really
inspires me
yeah in that sense at the highest level
right at the highest level to you
yeah to me i'm highly inspired by john
coltrane
i had a chance to tour with elvin jones
who was his drummer so i was able to
be sorcerer's apprentice for two years
yeah an amazing experience
i would say i really look up to
many of the european classical masters
stravinsky
litzt chopin bach beethoven brahms
rachmaninoff
debut c i look up to
hollywood film masters martin scorsese i
look at
um german impressionistic master
f w mourinho i mean
there's so many geniuses and so many
diverse fields
to be inspired by and to me
the actual physicality or
device or technique that they're using
to access
the light shall we say the light is
somewhat secondary i just am inspired
that these people
touch the light i mean simone biles this
gymnast that's out now is doing amazing
things
the williams sisters michael jordan
moving um steve jobs
i mean einstein newton
there's just so many numerous people
i i'm inspired by the existential fact
that they even existed
okay well this look this is in in large
part what the portal is all about and
just to open something up and i think
this is the perfect episode to do it i
haven't said it before
there are the n is often too low
in any particular field the number of
true geniuses like if i think about
physics there are lots of people who
would be considered geniuses in any
other field but like the top level
it's five people or less than the last
century you know
and so you have to aggregate over field
by field by field
if you want to see the pattern and in
some sense that's what i hear you saying
is
that you're looking you're not going to
let the instrument
define where you look for inspiration
and what you port back into your
own craft sure there are
specific dynamics to executing
behaviors ideas upon a particular
device or medium the inspiration
for that sort of thing in my case comes
from
multiple places which i'm sure is the
same for
many people as far as within the field
who really inspires me like i i would
say john coltrane
and art tatum from the perspective of
how they merged extreme
extreme technical mastery
of their given instruments
how they merged that with
a profound quote in-house
i'm referring to in their own mind in
their own flesh yeah
a profound in-house understanding
of where to put the music and
what approaches to take
similar to a chess player in the sense
that a chess game if you know how the
pieces move
okay cool yeah and if you as long as
you're
functioning in some kind of way that you
can either digitally
or physically move pieces around you can
be part of the game
so now how do the levels begin how do
you get from there to magnus carlsen
right
and so that internal game of okay why
did you decide to defend this
when in fact the greater attack was
coming over here you know that kind of
stuff okay so there's a great
analogy with jazz in a weird way which
is if i go back
to the guy i think of as potentially the
greatest creative genius
of jazz arguably would be louis
armstrong
who sort of invented modern jazz from
the hot fives hot sevens
not just like the jelly roll mortons of
the world
that is understandable to me in the same
way that a game of like
morphy or capoblanca was understandable
when chess was sort of in an earlier
stage of its development
but as both of these fields progressed
you always have this problem which is
that
the greater play loses the casual
observer
like they can't figure out what's going
on and i i
i bring this up in the context of
something i saw you hanging out with
herbie hancock and it warmed my heart
i heard him describe playing with miles
yes and he said i hit a chord that was
so
wrong and so off i wanted to clutch my
head
and he said what i didn't know is that
there was a level of musicianship beyond
this
where miles heard the same chord and
figured out the exact right notes to
play
that made it the right chord in arrears
and it was a keyboard player
you know talking about a trumpet player
who was
fixing his mistake because he didn't
hear it as a mistake he just heard it as
notes
to be played with and i think about that
in in terms of like the improvisational
idiom
yes and there are levels and levels and
levels and they lose us as casual
observers like
would we have known that moment happened
if we were in that club
or at that recording date if we weren't
at the top level of the profession
well i think as they say if you have a
good plumber
you never know anything's wrong right so
i think
we're in the business of not letting the
audience know that anything has gone
wrong
now analyzing the word wrong and that
sort of kind of a thing
that's where a matter of skill and
understanding come into play we're
talking about phenomenology
at that point we're talking about event
horizons we're talking about
existentialism at that point let me be
slightly less obtuse in the
world of film scoring yeah i think
bernard harmon was the one
who made the famous statement about the
great paradox that exists
in music where a piece of music could
quote unquote be terrible
you know it could be really weak bad
have a lot of inconsistencies
fail at a lot of different levels
clearly be
mediocre in its aspirations and its
execution of those aspirations
however however
with the right visual apparatus going
with it
with the right film going with it
suddenly that piece of music is the
penultimate
apex zenith of yeah the perfection
for that particular moment this is the
great paradox
so similarly when herbie played that
chord
yeah miles definitely aware of this
type of paradox can come to that
and put a sound with it
that transcends one aspect of sonority
transcends one aspect of analysis and
speaks
as miles davis said a higher level of
theory
it speaks to a higher level of theory if
you're
coming from the perspective that any
sound
is just a sound free of bias free of
predestination
you suddenly have expanded your toolbox
and so then it just becomes a question
of how familiar
are you with employing
these quote out of the box oh i love the
source of effects
and manipulating that sort of kind of
thing
you know this joke that leonard
bernstein put into west side story
where he takes the the most dissonant
interval
the tritone right and he goes marie
which is like
it goes to the fifth which is like the
most consonant and then he's like the
most beautiful word i ever
heard maria right and the whole idea is
that
the release from maximal tension into
maximum sonority
is the most gorgeous thing so he's going
to take the ugliness
and just serve it up as like this is you
know the the
feeling of just having met your true
love um
in screenwriting conflict yeah and
tension
are the building blocks of your story i
mean
that's drama that's irony night and day
these are the binaries these are the
opposites
life and death pain pleasure
happy sad all of these things
opposites there was a philosophy of
aesthetic realism that one of my
professors in
manhattan school of music would talk
about and
i don't want to butcher their tenants
however one thing did stick out they
would always talk about was how
the coming together of opposites is how
beauty forms or you know is the the
component
of beauty and so you know
while i might not necessarily call it
beauty or you know
put that term to it movement
speaking of counterbop right speaking of
bebop speaking of improvisation
movement is the core issue
i mean even getting down to
neurosciences the brain enables
movement moving topics around moving
pieces moving music moving people
movement movement movement dance
movement choreography
movement movement how you use harmony
how you use
writing how you use words all of these
things
work towards that same thing movement
einstein said when asked about the
universe
when asked about god something's moving
yeah there's something moving so
and yet he froze it in space-time the
whole concept of space-time
freezes the wave and so there's
something profound about the fact that
his insight
arguably got rid of movement by putting
time as part of the substrate
so you know and this is going to come up
when we talk about
cubism where you have been
on this new project which is
again once once again seemingly
increasing the dimensionality of
independence like parts
no longer it's just two parts of your
hands being independent like multiple
parts of the same hand are now
independent
um and that goes back to like duchamp
with the nude descending staircase which
was a somewhat something of a reference
to space and time where the tube
of the nude like one human form
creates a tube over time do you see that
you're playing with
sort of concepts that are coming out of
this
science-inspired exploration and the
tension
even internal to somebody like einstein
is it movement or is it frozen
i'm quite inspired by
neuroanatomy and i'm quite inspired by
physics
a good buddy of mine is far more
articulate about math and physics than i
am he's you know a big devotee
of that stuff and he's a musician his
name's
marcus miller not the bass player he's a
saxophone player yeah
but he's really interesting and so he
and i you know talk about stuff like
that
i tend more towards the
neuroanalytical side of things so i'm
very interested in
the human the homunculus and i'm
interested in the hippocampus and
the corpus corpus colossus and how the
different hemispheres of the brain
enable movement which plays directly
into my coordination so i explore
those kinds of spaces i explore how we
perceive time
less so than the actual substrate of
time itself
and you know although i do ponder those
things
i am very concerned with what's going on
under the hood you know what's
going on in the mind i like to analyze
transcripts of conversations between
someone who has dementia versus someone
who has alzheimer's
and listen to them talk to each other
and how they understand each other
because to me
that's the same as like two pieces of
music being played at the same time
you know because when something
makes no sense yeah at the
language level yeah or it's incoherent
the only way that we have to try to
glean anything from it is by analyzing
it
from a different perspective so if i
analyze it as music
like the rhythm of my voice you see what
i'm saying
these are the kinds of techniques and
manners and methods of analysis
that start to come into how i go about
assessing genius pursuing genius
and pursuing challenges and pursuing
fluidity
at what i do and so getting back to that
question of miles davis and kenny g
yeah again we're starting we're starting
to get into topics
that form the substrate of
analysis these are the all these topics
are the components of a platform of
analysis
through which i ponder
the event horizon of of music and
musicians
so like lex luthor said
to otis and superman you know there's
some people
who can swerve some people can movement
some people can look at the contents of
a bubble gum rapper
yeah and people figure out the secrets
of the universe
yeah what i'm saying so that's the thing
so
if we want to pejoratively what call
kenny g a bubble gum rapper but yeah
actually i know you didn't i'm not
accusing you that
all right i'm just saying yeah i'm just
saying but so many people normally do
this is why i'm the reason i chose just
folks at home the reason i chose kenny g
was that he was accessible i agree and
just like bubble gum
bubble gum people would argue people
would argue right
that his music is bubble gum compared to
a filet mignon or a few well where i was
going next with that
is is that if i think about two records
of miles
uh bitches brew versus kind of blue sure
bitch's brew was pretty challenging even
though it was trying to be a little bit
more in the rock idiom sure
kind of blue despite the fact that it is
unbelievable musicianship was inviting
and it became so iconic because
it worked at so many different levels it
didn't intrinsically
tell me you know uh bug off kid
this is for experts only it said this is
the highest level of musicianship
and it's going to work in a way that you
can put it on
without having to you know just
break your head over when i think about
art tatum
when i used to put the needle onto my
vinyl art tatum albums
i would only do it if i was in some
place to receive
the brilliance of this person that i
could not possibly understand
he was playing so fast and so
technically
at such a different level i mean i would
would it be fair to say that many
pianists consider art tatum
you know at the absolute maybe even
the top guy ever to play jazz piano sure
many would
and then there would be those there's a
claim that it's not that musical i can't
you know go contrary to that and
yeah that's okay but just some some
people at home have never heard of art
tatum at all
at another level there's
different times for different things and
different moods
to every scene too yeah right you know
there's situations where art tatum's
best would be inappropriate or
counterproductive
that's what very few circumstances in my
life do i
think wow i really just want to hear
some art tatum the only situation i'm in
when i really
feel that for myself and again not as a
musician
is when i want to remember what the
human mind is capable of
and this is the great conundrum this is
the great paradox because
as we were saying someone
could hear kenny g's silhouette for
instance
and experience profound tranquility and
serendipity they could listen to yanny
and get that there's people
if you go to youtube you can look at a
comment and someone would say
oh he's the mozart of our generation
something like that so incredulity
yeah is there's i'm sure of course
you've heard of it the
the fallacy of the incredulity fallacy
where just because it's impossible for
you to
find believable makes it
untrue so similarly
there's only a certain threshold that
classifying or dissecting
validity or worth can go and
you know let me put it to you this way
there's a story about charlie parker
where he was at a club and he was
listening to a guy play
that was to everyone else's opinion
you know really weak but charlie parker
was like really into checking it out
and he was able to hear things inside of
what that guy was doing or what that guy
was going for
that gave him ideas and
i think when i was first starting out
with rock jazz
that was something that i experienced
in a different kind of way where when i
first
started hearing some of these young
bands
and i would hear some of their live
shows on the internet at that time
on youtube i would think to myself man
this
doesn't really sound that great but the
people are loving it yeah and so then
that caused me to
have a different thought process about
hmm
maybe there's other aspects that are in
play that
connect to people's enjoyment of things
and so you know it really called some
things into question you know
it really caused me to think about
things
from multiple perspectives and
basically it threw me into the ocean
suddenly
it's just like what we see in politics
where you can feel really strongly about
a particular thing then you can find out
that
there's others that feel
even potentially for the exact same
reasons that you feel strongly about a
thing
for those exact same reasons they feel
the exact opposite thing
and it can be very a very incredulous
sort of kind of situation i i bring up
this example of dolly parton writing
this
brilliant song jolene and if you look at
the lyrics they're incredibly tight and
economical and conveying so much
more through implication than they even
state explicitly
jack white heard the song record it with
the white stripes turned it into a
pre-murder ballad singing the
female song from a male in a male voice
and dolly parton i believe wrote him a
letter saying you may understand
something about guitar but you
understand nothing about women but i
think the joke was on her that she'd
written such a brilliant song
that she didn't realize that it was now
approachable from a completely different
angle that she hadn't
had the last word on her own song so
there are all of these
weird and that reminds me of the
difference between
newtonian physics model versus
einstein's
physics and models and you know the
quantum theory and things of that nature
how
i might be misstating this correct me if
i'm wrong
that classical physics
start to break down at the quantum level
you would say that classical physics is
recoverable from the deeper model but
only as an approximation to the true
physics
within a regime and
he but you know we nobody has thrown
away newtonian physics because of
einstein because where it works you
don't need the extra einsteinian
perspective now that was an amazing stay
trapped did you trap me in something
no you just said something cool though
you just said something that
blows the whole thing open very nicely
tell me
well we don't need necessarily
x we don't need to discard
x in this location or we don't
necessarily need to bring in
y to this location so we can substitute
art tatum for rachmaninoff yeah we can
algebraically plug in kenny g miles we
can plug
in whichever artists or things that we
want to in a thing
and have that same exact dichotomy of
this works in this particular space eric
i totally
you see where i'm going with that so
similarly
let's just say people want to have a
romantic evening but eric
look there is an aspect of this that i'm
fighting which
you're making a very deep point that
whatever moves you whether it's the way
the performer looks
or the the feel of the evening
there is the total effect on the on the
audience and the listener from having
been present at a performance
there is also something which i can't
get escape which is you're just at a
different level than just about anybody
i ever
meet and you we can play around with
that and you know i play a little bit of
piano
i know when i'm being uh
when i'm in the presence of greatness
and you are at a different
level than almost anybody i've ever met
and you don't have to say anything back
but it's an
uncomfortable thing to hear we can talk
about the fact that
who knows maybe taylor swift is as
musically interesting as mile davis it's
a reasonable
that's not what i'm saying that that's
not what i'm saying okay
let's look at it from a different
perspective yes another perspective
let's look at it from a dj perspective
all right what is a dj's job a dj's job
one of the jobs of a dj is to curate
yeah
and present music right for people for a
particular occasion
to elicit either a certain response or
to provide an atmosphere that the venue
or the client is interested in
now if we take that down to a
microcosmic level
inside of our own head take it to the
piano for instance
take it to these instrumental scenarios
each note that i decide to play in that
nanosecond in that microsecond right i
decide to play it
that's the same as me djing that note
is a track now imagine
how many notes that you would hear in
the average performance and then
in my case i'm going to play a zillion
notes
right yeah so then that's a zillion
tracks
that i've dropped in a particular moment
or a particular session
so i'm trying to get into how
mental processes are uniform
whether it's at a hyper slow speed
yeah or a hyper fast speed yeah
the same process is there so this
conversation that we're having
might seem nebulous or maybe even
evasive on my part
or vague in my part or non-committal no
i should tell people that in general
when you and i talk
what i get is a time release
understanding of your points over the
next three or four days as they finally
make sense to me so
i'm going to challenge my audience i
told them at the beginning of this show
that i would never
spoon feed them you are a more
challenging person to talk to because
quite frankly your perspective is just
richer and you speak in an unusual
fashion and i
quite frankly it takes me days to
understand what conversation we just had
usually
well i i appreciate the accolades and i
love you too
eric and i i really love you i just
admire what you've done for us and i'm
going to blow people's mind by just
letting you be you
but it is important to know that these
levels of being exist and that's part of
why the show is called the portal is
that you are
in touch with something that most people
have no idea is even available
well i will say that
i do find inspiration
having recovered from
heavy depression and heavy panic attacks
even
sort of debilitating ones that it's
inspiring
for me to
try to share perspectives
that
hopefully some people could use to get a
different angle on their sufferings say
like when i talk about some of these
things or when i answer your questions
a certain sort of type of way
some of these techniques some of these
ways that i'm managing myself
also help me manage stress
help me manage depression helped me
manage
panic attacks and you've had anger i've
seen anger and you've certainly
yeah anger anger control things of that
nature
fury rage and it also helps me get a
higher chest rating too
because well think about the godfather
for a moment
remember how the james khan character
sunny yeah ran out the house because
carlo was being you know he was being
super aggressive to his sister
but then the bad guys realized oh that's
the way to get him out there because
he'll jump on that
and so then they manipulate the toba
yeah they manipulated
his anger they manipulated one aspect
that was predictable about him
and they manipulated that to get out
there so similarly i think within
ourselves
there are certain weak spots or
different things
that can manipulate us whether we want
to or not
into bad situations or you know whether
it's a micro bad situation or macro bad
situation
and so it's important to develop
techniques
to manage those kinds of things ergo
box well tempered clavier
so i always wondered why because as
growing up as a kid i was like why is it
called well
tempered what does that mean i only know
one kind of temper
um well well anyway
all of these particular devices and
techniques and responses
all played to trying to
find the most accurate
answer and you know find the most
accurate way
to approach
a situation and that's a very musical
thing
how do we approach this we see it in
chess too
how do we approach this position it's
your move you've got to make a move
the clock is ticking how do we approach
this you can see it in screenwriting
okay i've got this idea i want to have
this character save the world
how do we approach this okay i'm at the
piano
the people are waiting for the next tune
okay i've got this idea i'm
playing something with my left hand and
i've got this idea that i want to
bring out i've got this energy that i'm
feeling i've got this inspiration
but how do i approach it how do i bring
this thing
in to existence existential reality
right aesthetic reality how do i do this
intentions oftentimes
are not enough right it has to
match up with execution you know
that's when we start to get into the
conversation of levels now again
it can become a debated and
subjective thing and that particular
stalemate
the getting back to the kenny g miles
davis thing yeah
that particular stalemate only gets
broken by something
objective when we're faced with
subjectivity
that seems endless yeah then that
stalemate
gets broken by the simple question of
okay who's going to pay for it
ultimately
so who's going to hire miles davis right
who's going to hire kenny g
now that can get to the lament that you
were referring to earlier
in the big picture well then you have
these problems of like the comedian's
comedian can't get hired but all the
people who can get hired look to that
person and they say
that's the guy who's really got it going
on this is the confusion about this
now the thing quite you know i'm just
going to over
you're an overwhelming presence i'm
going to try to overwhelm you right back
okay
one of the things that i love about your
playing is is that you're playing at
this incredibly technical level it's so
inventive but you bring
so much soul and so much showmanship and
the branding the whole thing is going on
whatever layer of the stack i want to
plug into it's available to me
if i want to just have the most
beautiful tunes
you're providing that if i want to see
something new and innovative it's
happening
and what i've seen is you know and i
this is a little bit off color
it's like you make love to a room of
3000 people at a time and
just everybody is locked in there
everybody's in the pocket everybody's
feeling the groove and
we're thinking and we're feeling at
different levels i think maybe one of
my mistakes here is is that i need to
get you in front of the piano first
have you play us some stuff and then
when we talk about these levels i'm not
going to be
quite as back footed i shouldn't
probably shouldn't have done the kenny g
thing just because people will well
people will infer
that i meant something from it that i
didn't but it's not so be it
i just i disagree with you all right i
think that it was perfect
i think that it's actually a spectacular
thing because it's really going to be
a type of provocative
and easily recognizable maybe people
will distinction
yeah well yeah i mean it gets back to
one of the other points that you were
making with regards to distinction
yeah how do we tell things apart so we
have to use
things that are very distinct in order
for us to have a distinction in the
conversation
i mean that's the same thing that
happens in
great film if your premise or your
opening part of your film
lacks yeah a strong enough of a
distinction
about a situation that particular
lackage
deficiency is going to haunt the film
the whole time
you know um
the premise of dirty dancing
there's this professional dancer and
there's this competition
and he wants to win that his partner
ends up having
and super dangerous super
harmful i guess illegal just terrible
abortion and then there's this rich girl
whose father is a doctor
who saves her life that woman's life
but now she can't dance and so then
the daughter now who is a klutz has to
be
taught how to dance so that this guy can
go ahead and win the competition but it
has to happen in secret now because the
father
you know it's the pl that however it
struck me
it blew me away that such a
an amazingly painful controversial topic
right such as abortion right you know
such an amazingly painful
excruciatingly mind-bendingly
sad topic and divisive
divisive yeah yet
tell that story yet this is a dance
at the finale the dance and the finale
we see that at weddings
on online you can see yeah different
couples trying to do that
so when it came out in the
you know cinematically or as far as
storytelling
the power of such a
topic that seems what is that
particularly what does that mean
have to do with a dance competition but
think about it
as a screenwriter i thought about it if
you take that out
right then you're sitting with pen and
paper and you're like okay well i've got
this dance competition i've got this
dancer
i've got this klutz so the the good guy
that you know the great dancer
needs to teach this klutz right how to
dance so that he can win the competition
now if you replace that other scenario
with
multiple types of problems you'll find
that it's hard to get something as
compelling
as that however that person took a heavy
risk now the
screenwriter was a woman so then she
yeah the screenwriter is a woman and she
was a mambo dancer and
she was her father was a doctor and she
went to country clubs and so she
experienced this dickens like type of
life where
you know there's rich and poor and you
know all these kinds of things and i'm
sure her father
was you know warning her about the um
the
the dangers of sexual activity and you
know
pitfalls and what he's seen and stuff
like that so she put that all together
so perhaps because she had an experience
with it and she's a woman
that she was able to speak on those
subjects so
amazingly and she had the understanding
of how to bring
those subjects together because she
lived it right you know
however it wouldn't occur to the average
person but this is what we call
genius you know what i'm saying that's
genius and it's lasted the test of time
but that's my whole point with why
the whole opening and this gets back to
what you're talking about when we're
talking about genius and things like
nature
you did a genius thing yet you're trying
to get me
to discount that or go away from that
but i'm
identifying you're a genius and that
ties to what i was saying about
how charlie parker would hear a guy that
people would say
what's he talking about but he's
listening intently
that's the whole point you see all these
things come together if you've
created this podcast as the example of
the thing that we were talking about in
the podcast yeah these are wheels within
wheels
yeah this is the universe is within
universes quantum it all breaks down at
this level but it holds at this level
this is why we love having you over for
shabbat
all that kind of thing so you did it
from the very beginning all right your
instinctive
thing you i didn't force you to choose
those names
yeah you naturally chose those names
all i'm doing yeah is the same thing
that i would do inside of my mind
if i get an idea the sensor yeah filter
in my mind's like wow
that's actually pretty cool because i'm
referencing all these other things i'm
seeing all this stuff
it's just like a chess game i'm seeing
the checkmate i'm like wow this king
is positioned over here okay i've got to
do this in such a way that by the time
i'm going to spring this trap
he doesn't even see that that subtle
move he made actually provides
the funny thing is i think i chose kenny
g if i recall correctly
yeah because i think i remember hearing
that he had had
he had actually been an innovator with
some circular breathing technique
and that he was somebody who was seen as
being middle of the road but actually
a good deal above that in musicianship
so i think i had some different process
i wish it was that i had some some super
clever idea but it was probably only one
one or two moves deep but thank you for
saying it still
functions well that's the but because
through dancing
i get to dance with you so so you get to
do what
miles did to my herbie hancock move and
just like in
dirty dancing he had to take what she
was doing
right and from what i've understood
about dancing
in that particular format it's the man's
role
in traditionally to showcase
the female yeah he's more of
basically a pole you know a static
figure that's
showcasing all the things that she can
do that's what makes a good
male dance partner i don't know how
things work as far as
you know how we're identifying and you
know on political roles these days
however i think traditionally that's
kind of how well i think it's a
beautiful aspect to this concept that
healthy male female relations and
heterosexual context
have to do with passing power back and
forth and so the idea is that he might
have the responsibility of leading
which people will say well that's an
impressive act but then if the idea is
no but it's not just that i'm leading my
role
is also to become the substrate to
showcase your abilities
these kinds of dynamics have broken as
we've gotten very
simplistic in saying well that's that's
power that's oppression
and not recognizing that these things
are part of an interwoven whole
um right so you know the idea is that if
i if i
evaluate myself as a podcaster and i'm
just thinking about myself and i'm not
thinking about the dynamic of the
conversation because i'm just learning
this this is like
i'm eight episodes in or something like
that right um
yeah you know it's it's a question of i
need to learn
more yes and because of the
improvisational idiom
that podcasting is so right
and and improvisation
is everywhere everyone's doing it each
word we speak
is improvised we're drawing from a
vocabulary we're putting
concepts and ideas to sound we're using
light utilizing these instruments
and we're bringing out energy and we're
moving
things around to create a type of
movement
progression and these are all the things
that get depicted
in art all over the place so a lot of
times it's very easy
to
[Music]
find genius or brilliances brilliancies
the hard part can be to
after you've managed to identify it yeah
accurately that is to stay with it
and then bring in enough
tradition or enough substantiation
to further demonstrate why that thing is
genius that's been my mission in this
particular conversation i thought
fantastic pivoting between the kenny g
and the miles davis element was
brilliant and it provided such
a great foundation for the conversation
because we could have gone we can go
further we can talk about how
kenny g racially is very interesting in
fact
that was one of the things yeah well
that was one of the things that inspired
me as
ilu was the idea that
there was a huge number
of black people that really got into
this guy playing soprano saxophone they
were really into it
and they made him rich you know
much to the consternation of many black
jazz musicians
who couldn't understand how a white
musician like that could get such
loyalty i know nothing money from
do you have an answer as to what target
demographic
well because some things transcend
quote color
it is what it is some things transcend
that
for different reasons for different
reasons
so part of ilu was also an experiment
because i was thinking well that's
interesting what if i tried that
in reverse what if i
a quote-unquote black guy from a murder
capital from camden new jersey
yeah look it up folks camden new jersey
there's a rolling stone article called
apocalypse new jersey the sad story of
camden
to get a sense of where i'm from native
of that place
what would happen yeah if i
who has spent my life learning miles
davis learning art tatum learning
all of this traditional quote black
music yeah what if i learned how to play
the rolling stones what if
i learned how to play nirvana what if i
learned
how to play that stuff because when i
was doing the traditional thing
i won the biggest competition in jazz i
got a full scholarship
thelonious monk competition yeah i won
the felonious monk international piano
competition
i had also gotten a full scholarship to
manhattan school of music
which i graduated dean's list all of
these types of athletes i toured the
world with wynton marcellus yeah but
i couldn't get a record deal which is
always i mean this is when i talked
about your anger
right i couldn't get a record i was so
flabbergasted to hear this
right and then the idea that you figured
out this hack
which is right which is and that's what
we're getting into here so when we talk
about when you talk about kenny g
miles davis it it goes deep into a lot
of
aspects for me because i looked at him i
looked at yanni i looked at liberace
right and i was like wow they have
massive followings
if you took them to
downtown new york's jazz scene
how distinctive would they be as far as
skill level goes
relative to you know your average
college musician
or post-college musician so then
that was where i got the idea to
well one of the places that i got an
idea to do an experiment well what would
happen
if a quote unquote black guy from the
hood
decided to start expertly playing sweet
home alabama
which i ended up playing on america's
got talent the enigma of that
the speaking of elephants in the room
right right
the elephant in the room is you see this
guy i mean sure the average person is
going to say oh i don't see color
oh wow you're just playing sweet home
alabama but
you know i don't know i i kind of don't
think so i don't think it's just that
but either way
that's my point so i sought to
see if the same thing could be true in
reverse
and sure enough it did
now i didn't write my own music the way
kenny g wrote like silhouette i didn't
use
drum beats and things of that nature and
so there's relativity as far as you know
degrees of success with that
however i did achieve a very okay but
like even even in this situation just to
rip off of it
you know this uh movie victor victoria
the story of a woman playing a man
playing a woman
a female female impersonator
right right okay so you're telling me
when you do satisfaction
that you're actually swerving and
feeding the rolling stones black
back to white audiences potentially a
very visibly black man
on the other hand there's this beautiful
video of keith richards
taking apart and dissecting satisfaction
and he says you want to know where
what it is and he starts playing it as
like a mississippi blues on the guitar
and so you realize that he took this
this riff
you know off of the fifth six flat seven
uh
you know typical blues pattern disguised
it and now you're sort of
weirdly the black guy playing a white
guy
playing black music feeding it back to
white audiences
and in some sense giving this really
beautiful
um and friendly middle finger to this
whole
notion of race dividing us that we have
to both
note it because it does exist and it
influences us no matter how much we deny
it on the other hand
it doesn't have to preoccupy us
constantly and be the only thing i i
always think about
you know this race and iq point that
keeps coming up i never see this
happening
among people who are deep into music
because the the contributions have been
so profound from everywhere
that it just is like why
why are you exploring these ideas
that clearly don't capture who has
contributed and how much has been done
for me chess has been
a great liberator or a great questioner
of some of these more quote race
driven concepts
because i learned chess from basically
black street hustlers
in washington square park and they
prefer speed chess
yeah blitz guys yeah and so they
had great aspiration or sorry great
admiration
and aspiration towards some of the
russian gm's and
just to hear these men who are the
epitome of soul
the epitome the epitome of quote
blackness
yeah flavor all of that stuff rhythm all
of that stuff
to hear them use about capablanca or to
pull out
a game nimzovich
or tau or some of these great masters
to you know go over those games and say
well see he's a killer here no hold on
hold on wait a minute now
we gotta watch the bishop watch the
bishop boom okay
okay he saw that he saw me coming huh
like just all of the snaps i remember
getting into about the conversation
washington square park about tigran
petrossian
the chess player and these guys were
like convinced that somehow he hadn't
been understood for
for the the soul that he was bringing to
the game right
so for me to get around that was like
very
striking because at that time i was
really starting to feel
you know my depression was coming in my
panic was coming in
because in my thoughts i'm like wow
i've won the monk competition i've
towed the line full scholarship came
from camden
full scholarship graduated all this
stuff but
the powers that be don't find me
i guess marketable enough to have me
be a representative of their agency you
know in the form of a recording artist
so i really started to have some really
mind-bendingly rageful and
you know things going on in my head and
and
i noticed that there were some other
artists
quote-unquote white artists that were
starting to experiment with rock
in the jazz lane they were getting jazz
record deals but they were
working with rock concepts overtly
questioning does jazz have to swing and
things of that nature
that me from the wynton marcellus
purest background and aspiration i would
never
question does jazz have to swing right
so there was a lot of
anger starting to build up from a couple
of different places from
you could say a political aspect and
also from a personal aspect
because i'm like i can't even get a
record deal here like
how good do i have to play what do i
have to prove here and
ultimately who are you guys to judge
whether i'm worthy of a record deal or
you know i it kind of got into these
kind of simplistic and
superficial angers diminish and this is
one of the reasons to be blunt about it
since i heard you play first i don't
know
close to 10 years ago but maybe in
person a little bit less
i've often thought i have to be
promoting this guy not because he's not
going to get famous on his own but
because he shouldn't have to say
what doesn't need it just doesn't need
to be said i
when i watch you in a room
everyone knows something amazing has
happened and if i could just tell one
story from our personal life
we were having dinner my wife and i with
sam harris and he was fading in san
francisco
and i said hey do you want to go over
and hear a friend of mine play a little
piano it didn't sound very inviting i
wasn't going to tell him anything more
so he says you know fine if it's quick
so we get him over to this place and
you're there
we go over and there's this old beat up
steinway and there's a crowd of people
who are sitting around waiting to hear
you play
and this one woman will not be quiet
she's just not
calming down she's on her phone and you
say something like
hey something amazing is about to happen
you're about to have a life-altering
experience you need to be
in the right frame of mind
and everybody in the room who knew you
knew what was about to happen and
everyone in the room who didn't know you
said what nothing nothing nobody talks
like this
the room quieted down i've never seen
sam harris so deep in meditation
he was his whole world was like re-woven
uh with with the music you were playing
and he was just speechless at the end of
it
and we all stayed up late into the night
um
there is something uh in this which is
it doesn't need to be said i don't know
why
it's so hard to get through because the
music does speak for itself but i think
it goes back to your just wheels within
wheels curation one of the things i
wanted to do and you were one of the
people i had in mind when i started this
podcast
was i wanted to show people what is
possible in their lives and
i'll be honest with you you have two
separate effects on me sometimes
i hear you and i just sit down at the
piano and i want to play play play
and get better and other times i don't
want to touch it i don't want to look at
it because i know i'm never going to be
at that level and it is difficult and
uncomfortable
to work with genius and to and to see it
in in a field in which you're just
playing and you're never going to aspire
to be
at the top of what you might be able to
achieve that particular
night
i know that you're paraphrasing or you
know recalling
i know how i get when i feel as though
there's a person that's violating
things for others so
i don't recall my exact words
i'm pretty sure that i wouldn't call
attention to myself in the sense of hey
i'm about to do something amazing
in in in that sense if i did it wasn't
from a narcissistic standpoint eric it
wasn't
i don't know if you remember this she
came up to me and she said he was
absolutely right
that that said um i just want to kind of
clarify that because i don't want
to create the impression of a naked
narcissistic egotistical kind of thing
that's not my point
you did say something like that but it
was the feeling of it if i if for me
it's just that she was ruining a
situation you've got sam harris there
you've got people there
and she's you know bringing a scenario
that ultimately no one else
was going to sort of deal with it and so
actually she's making a choice for
everybody and this is why you see this
so then i had to make a choice as well
this
is the thing how often do you have a
conductor who stops a performance
of an orchestra you know of 50 people
because somebody's cell phone goes off
right this is now a common feature we
don't make the room for
opening our hearts and i think to be
blunt about it
um i'm sorry if i told the story in a
way that didn't convey it but what
what actually happened was that we all
did have a communal experience that
we're still talking about you know and i
i can tell you that there are small
number of performances
the time i saw prince open for the
rolling stones uh
the time that i saw a
clarinet player blow
dizzy gillespie off stage that i'd never
heard of named tony scott
they're a very small number of things
that actually just change your life and
this is one of those
that was one of those nights on the
other side
i've come to understand over
time what aspects
of my playing and also what aspects of
my
personal behavior or presentation
have been detrimental to my
progression in certain aspects of the
business
so i also want to make sure that
i bring in that aspect
to because it's very immature also
to come with a knights templar kind of
perspective
we've seen that and we've heard that and
that also is not brilliant because
the fact of the matter is there are many
reasons and many contributing factors
many dynamics that play into
careers into
helium into buoyancy and
the like and so
over time i've come to understand a lot
more about how energy works and how
i've been very good at transforming the
energy in a room
and you know bringing people to these
types of ecstasies
however there was another aspect that i
was
less concerned with now i think that
because of the panic attacks and the
depression and stuff like that
i was a lot less sensitive to it because
in the anger
as well however as time has gone by
i've gotten better i've improved my
technique and
i've grown
through anger and i've found ways to
harness
anger and panic attacks and depression
and bring it into the music in a
powerful way and in a
a technical way it's caused me to have
even more vision
and my chest rating has improved so i'm
able to i'm
able to analyze myself and realize
just because i could raise the roof on a
place
didn't necessarily provide
a blank check for me to get a record
deal they're looking at other aspects
and those aspects are important too like
see this is
and this gets a game back to the kenny g
miles davis
um um
construct the model because
one thing that i didn't understand
if i'm going to work with a record label
yeah
then i'm making an implicit statement
there
i'm saying that i want to be a part of
their
family right i'm saying that i want to
represent them
at multiple levels now
i was coming from a very uncompromising
place
i was coming from a very
narrow we could say place
i also was sub aware
of how i sound it
in in certain aspects these days i've
come to understand
as i've gotten so much better i've
come to understand wow there are so many
other aspects
you didn't have the luxury back then i
mean if i can be honest about it
sure i'm not really ready to be in front
of the world
it's very terrifying having a podcast
because i don't have all my stuff sorted
out
but nobody does nobody does and one of
the things back then
is you were you were a terrifying guy
because you were completely
uncompromising
you know and i get in there and i try to
have a musical conversation with you and
you're very patient with me
but inevitably you know it shows the
levels that we're at
and you know i could see how
exacting you were you have been driving
yourself
you were in a competition with you alone
so far as i can tell at the piano
and you've been pushing yourself farther
and farther and
i i love the fact that you're getting
the recognition and that it's giving you
the luxury to look at yourself and then
as your mental state goes up the vision
expands
your chest rating improves but we also
have to honor
that it may be that it is as a
developmental stage and just to turn it
back to the kenny g
miles thing that we want to shed
where we were i was in a narrow place i
was in an angry place
but sometimes that stuff is like
colostrum it's needed to get
going and you have to go through those
periods where you've got that anger and
furor because that's what causes things
to progress
and that advanced your story is quite
the it's quite the paradox
that i'll have to concede that that
that's very true
had i not been so angry had i
not had those issues rock
would have never appealed to me because
what rock enables one to express
yeah i wouldn't have had that to express
the lyrics of rock are
very different from the lyrics that
you'll find in a gershwin or a jazz tune
and it was those lyrics that provided me
some escape
from you know what it's called through
you to neil young and screw you to the
governor of alabama in the song
right right right and and to your point
about swing the word rock
transition from rock and roll where rock
is a rocking motion it's a verb
to rock where it's led zeppelin and it's
just a giant stone edifice and it
doesn't move
right and the same question comes up
with uh with jazz but let me ask you
can i lure you to the piano and
sort of explore some of these ideas with
me at the keyboard and
give my listeners a taste of what we're
talking about yup fantastic
[Music]
rhythm changes it's basically george
gershwin's
as far as counterpoint
okay
holy cow
yeah and i was also able to hear the
independence of the lines and i'm
assuming that that is
a good chunk improv it's all improved
[Music]
so
do
[Music]
so
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
do
[Music]
[Applause]
wow
[Music]
foreign
you
[Music]
so
foreign
[Music]
so
okay
[Music]
so
one uh
[Music]
so
thank you sir
[Music]
me
so
[Music]
[Applause]
so
[Music]
so doctor
thank you
all right you've been through the portal
with the maestro jesus himself mr eric
lewis
part of him is ilu he's all over the
internet and wherever you buy your music
and come out to see him in concert i
guarantee you've never seen this show
quite like it
and it'll be an amazing time that you
remember it forever
[Music]